- So there's a few
things going on here.
The cold water rapidly cools the
exterior surface of the glass,
hardening it almost immediately.
The interior, still
molten, cools more slowly.
As it cools, it contracts and
attempts to pull the surface
in with it, but it can't--
well, not very much.
The surface has
already hardened,
so it gets pulled in only
a little, compressing it,
while also creating an internal
layer that remains forever
under tension.
It is this action
that gives the glass
its uncharacteristic strength.
We call it compressive strength.
- It sounds like
the same principle
as how an arch provides strength
in structural engineering.
- Yes, kind of.
Now, Jamie, I'm going
to ask for your help.
We're going to attempt to
destroy this Prince Rupert
drop.
I just want you to tip that
hammer past its center point.
Go ahead.
That's what Peter
was talking about.
So you can hit it really hard.
- Now I feel like
we've been swindled.
- Swindled not.
We have just experienced--
That's good writing.
- --the power of
compressive strength.
It does, however,
have an Achilles heel.
Take those nippers right
there and nip the backside
of the tail of this
Prince Rupert drop
and watch what happens.
Wait, wait, wait, cue
the high-speed camera.
OK, here we go.
- Oh!
Here it comes.
- That was even cooler
than I thought it would be.
[END PLAYBACK]
So that's what
you just saw live.
And what that is is
it's a relief of--
thank you, or not.
[APPLAUSE]
Yeah, sure.